<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - ImprovementPedia -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_FISHING_BOATS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A fishing vessel is any boat or ship used to catch fish, at sea or on a lake or river. Many different vessels are used in commercial, artisanal and recreational fishing.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Un bateau de pêche est un navire pratiquant la pêche, que ce soit en mer, dans un lac ou une rivière. En général, le nom d'un type de bateaux est relation avec la pêche qu'il pratique, le type de poissons recherché ou la technique utilisée.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Ein Fischerboot ist ein kleines Seegefährt, dass entlang der Küste, in Flüssen oder in Seen zum Fischfang genutzt werden kann.</German>
		<Hungarian>[TAB]A halászhajó bármely olyan csónak vagy hajó, amelyet halak kifogására használnak a tengeren, tavon vagy folyón. A kereskedelmi, kézműves és szabadidős halászatban sokféle hajót használnak.</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_WINERY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A winery is a building or property that produces wine, or a business involved in the production of wine such as a wine company. Besides winemaking equipment, large wineries might have warehouses, bottling lines, laboratories, and extensive tank farms. The oldest winery in the world found so far is 6,000 years old, in the Areni region of Armenia, which is still a wine making region today.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Un vignoble est un espace dédié à la culture du vin. Les pentes ensoleillées étaient principalement utilisées à cet effet. Les plus anciennes traces de viticulture se trouvent en Arménie et remontent à près de 6000 ans.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Ein Weinberg oder ein Weinanbaugebiet ist ein Areal, das dem Weinanbau gewidmet ist. Meist wurden dazu sonnige Hanglagen genutzt. Die ältesten Weinanbaugebiete, die man je fand, lagen in Armenien und sind fast 6000 Jahre alt.</German>
		<Hungarian>[TAB]A borászat egy épület vagy birtok, ahol bort állítanak elő, vagy egy bortermeléssel foglalkozó vállalkozás, például egy borászati cég. Egyes vállalatok több borászatot is tulajdonolnak. A borászati berendezéseken kívül a nagy borászatok raktárakkal, palackozó sorokkal, laboratóriumokkal és kiterjedt tartályparkokkal is rendelkezhetnek. A világ legrégebbi, eddig felfedezett borászat 6000 éves és Örményország Areni régiójában található, amely ma is bortermelő régió.</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TERRAIN_SWAMP_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A swamp is a wetland that is forested. Many swamps occur along large rivers where they are critically dependent upon natural water level fluctuations. Other swamps are along the shores of large lakes. Some swamps have hummocks, or dry-land protrusions covered by aquatic vegetation, or vegetation that tolerates periodical inundation. The two main types of swamp are "true" or swamp forests and "transitional" or shrub swamps. In the boreal regions of Canada, the word swamp is colloquially used for what is more correctly termed a bog or muskeg. The water of a swamp may be fresh water, brackish water or seawater. Some of the world's largest swamps are found along major rivers such as the Amazon, the Mississippi and the Congo. Conservationists have worked hard to preserve swamps. For example, the swamps in Northwest Indiana have been preserved as part of the Indiana Dunes.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Un marécage désigne une zone recouverte de marais. Il est souvent situé à proximité d'un lac, d'une grande rivière ou de la mer (mangrove). Sa mise en valeur est un défi pour l'homme, car l'humidité est une contrainte importante aux nombreuses implications, y compris sanitaires (moustiques vecteurs de la malaria, par exemple).</French>
		<German>[TAB]Unter einem Sumpf versteht man ein Feuchtgebiet mit Baumbewuschs. Sie entstehen oft an angrenzenden Flüssen oder Seen.</German>
		<Hungarian>[TAB]A mocsár egy erdős vizes élőhely. Sok mocsár nagy folyók mentén található, ahol kritikus mértékben függnek a természetes vízszint-ingadozásoktól. Más mocsarak nagy tavak partján találhatók. Néhány mocsárban dombok vagy szárazföldi kiemelkedések találhatók, amelyeket vízi növényzet vagy időszakos elárasztást tűrő növényzet borít. A mocsarak két fő típusa a "valódi" vagy mocsári erdő és az "átmeneti" vagy cserjés mocsár. Kanada lombhullató régióiban a mocsár szót köznyelvben arra használják, amit helyesebben lápnak neveznek. A mocsár vize lehet édesvíz, brakkvíz vagy tengervíz. A világ legnagyobb mocsárjai az Amazonas, a Mississippi és a Kongó folyók mentén találhatók. A természetvédők keményen dolgoztak a mocsarak megóvásán. Például az északnyugat-indianai mocsarakat az Indianai Dűnék részeként őrzik.</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FEATURE_OASIS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]An oasis is an isolated area of vegetation in a desert, typically surrounding a spring. Oases provide habitat for animals and even humans if the area is big enough. Oases are critically important for trade routes in desert areas. Caravans must travel via oases to replenish water and food. Political or military control of an oasis means control of trade on a particular route. For example, the oases of Awjila, Ghadames and Kufra, situated in modern-day Libya, have been vital to both north-south and east-west trade in the Sahara.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Un·e oasis (du grec ancien óasis) désigne, en géographie, une zone de végétation isolée dans un désert. Cela se produit à proximité d'une source d'eau, lorsqu'une nappe phréatique est suffisamment proche de la surface du sol ou parfois sur le lit d'une rivière temporaire (oued).</French>
		<German>[TAB]Unter einer Oase versteht man eine isolierte Gegend mit Wasser und Vegetation, die von sehr trockenem Gebiet oder gar Wüste umschlossen ist. Sie stellen in diesen Gebieten Inseln des Lebens dar.</German>
		<Hungarian>[TAB]A földrajzban az oázis egy sivatagban elszigetelten fekvő növényzettel borított terület, amely általában egy forrás körül helyezkedik el. Az oázisok élőhelyet biztosítanak az állatoknak és ha a terület elég nagy, akkor az embereknek is. Az oázisok elhelyezkedése kritikus fontosságú volt a sivatagi területeken a kereskedelmi és közlekedési útvonalak szempontjából. A karavánoknak az oázisokon keresztül kellett utazniuk, hogy feltölthessék vízkészleteiket és élelmüket. Így az oázisok politikai vagy katonai ellenőrzése sok esetben egy adott útvonalon folyó kereskedelem ellenőrzését jelentette. Például az Awjila, Ghadames és Kufra oázisok, amelyek a mai Líbiában találhatók, különböző időpontokban mind az észak-déli, mind a kelet-nyugati kereskedelem szempontjából létfontosságúak voltak a Szaharában. Az oázis szó az angol nyelvbe a görög oasis szóból került be, amelyet közvetlenül az egyiptomi vagy demotikus nyelvből vettek át. Nem a kopt nyelvből vették át, ahogyan azt néha feltételezik; a görög szó már több évszázaddal a kopt nyelv írásbeli megjelenése előtt is létezett.</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FEATURE_FLOOD_PLAINS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A floodplain is a flat or nearly flat land next to a stream or river that stretches from the banks of its channel to the base of the enclosing valley walls and experiences flooding during periods of high discharge. It includes the floodway, which consists of the stream channel and adjacent areas that carry flood flows, and the flood fringe, which are areas covered by the flood, but which do not experience a strong current.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Une plaine inondable désigne l'espace relativement plat qui entoure un cours d'eau. Il peut être occupé en permanence ou de manière saisonnière, et sera inondé en cas de crue : on parle de lit de la rivière. La limite du lit majeur correspond au niveau de la plus grande crue historique enregistrée.</French>
		<German>[TAB]A floodplain, or flood plain, is a flat or nearly flat land adjacent to a stream or river that stretches from the banks of its channel to the base of the enclosing valley walls and experiences flooding during periods of high discharge. It includes the floodway, which consists of the stream channel and adjacent areas that carry flood flows, and the flood fringe, which are areas covered by the flood, but which do not experience a strong current.</German>
		<Hungarian>[TAB]Az árterület egy folyó vagy patak mellett elterülő sík vagy majdnem sík terület, amely a meder partjától a völgyfalak aljáig terjed és nagy vízhozamú időszakokban áradásnak van kitéve. Ide tartozik az árvízcsatorna, amely a patakmederből és a szomszédos, árvízvízzel elöntött területekből áll, valamint az árvízszél, amely az árvíz által elöntött, de erős áramlásnak nem kitett területekből áll.</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PEDIA_QUOTE</Tag>
		<English>Quote</English>
		<French>Citation</French>
		<German>Zitat</German>
		<Italian>Citazione</Italian>
		<Spanish>Cita</Spanish>
		<Russian>Цитата</Russian>
		<Hungarian>Idézet</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PEDIA_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Strategy</English>
		<French>Stratégie</French>
		<German>Strategie</German>
		<Italian>Strategia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Estrategia</Spanish>
		<Russian>Стратегия</Russian>
		<Hungarian>Stratégia</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MIGRATES</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Migrates from Europe</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Migre depuis l'Europe</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Migriert aus Europa</German>
		<Russian>[ICON_BULLET]Мигрирует из Европы</Russian>
		<Hungarian>[ICON_BULLET]Európából kivándorol</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BUYABLE_IN_EUROPE</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Buyable in Europe</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Recrutable en Europe</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Kaufbar in Europa</German>
		<Russian>[ICON_BULLET]Можно купить в Европе</Russian>
		<Hungarian>[ICON_BULLET]Európában megvásárolható</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BUYABLE_IN_AFRICA</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Buyable in Africa</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Recrutable en Afrika</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Kaufbar in Africa</German>
		<Russian>[ICON_BULLET]Можно купить в Африке</Russian>
		<Hungarian>[ICON_BULLET]Afrikában megvásárolható</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BUYABLE_IN_PORT_ROYAL</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Buyable in Port Royal</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Recrutable à Port Royal</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Kaufbar in Port Royal</German>
		<Russian>[ICON_BULLET]Можно купить в Порт Ройале</Russian>
		<Hungarian>[ICON_BULLET]Port Royalban megvásárolható</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TAUGHT_BY_NATIVES</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Trained by Natives</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Formé par les Indigènes</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Ausbildbar durch Ureinwohner</German>
		<Russian>[ICON_BULLET]Обучается у индейцев</Russian>
		<Hungarian>[ICON_BULLET]Indiánok képzik ki</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
